<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mans inbred malady, or The doctrine of original sin maintained, as also the necessity of infants baptism. / By George Burches B.D. late Rector of Wood-Church in Cheshire.</title>
            <author>Burches, George, d. 1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77834</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1708_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10375</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858828</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858828</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110887</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77834)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110887)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 212:E1708[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mans inbred malady, or The doctrine of original sin maintained, as also the necessity of infants baptism. / By George Burches B.D. late Rector of Wood-Church in Cheshire.</title>
                  <author>Burches, George, d. 1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 129, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Wilson, and are to be sold by Thomas Johnson at the Golden Key in Saint Paul's Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin, Original --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110887:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MANS INBRED MALADY, OR The Doctrine of Original Sin maintained, As alſo the neceſſity of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> GEORGE BURCHES <hi>B. D. late Rector of Wood-Church in</hi> Cheſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eph. 4.14</hi>
               </bibl> Henceforth be no more Children toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of Doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning craftineſſe whereby they lie in wait to deceive.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Arauſian Concil. 2. c. 2.</hi>
               </bibl> Si quis ſoli Adae praevaricationem ſuam non &amp; ejus propagini aſſerit nocuiſſe &amp;c. anathema.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Wilſon,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Johnſon</hi> at the Golden Key in Saint <hi>Paul's Church-yard.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:110887:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110887:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS HIGHNES; <hi>OLIVER</hi> Lord Protector of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland. G. B.</hi> wiſheth Eternall Honor and Happineſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is obſervable in the Catalogue of antient worthies that ſuch were accounted moſt eminent that arriving at the
<pb facs="tcp:110887:3"/> higheſt pitch of Honor, did prove moſt humble. Hence that famous Emperor <hi>Theodoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> eſteemed it a greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to be called <hi>membrum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae,</hi> then to bee ſtiled <hi>Caput Imperij.</hi> The ſervant of the Church, then the Soveraign of an Empire. Humility is that Grace that Eternizes the fame of all Gods worthies. Hence <hi>Joſhuah, David</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are renowned for ever, as moſt Eminent in fighting the Battels of the Great God: whoſe undertakings were Crown'd with the greateſt ſucceſſe for the advancement of the Cauſe of God. With no
<pb facs="tcp:110887:3"/> leſſe Honor and ſucceſſe hath it pleaſed the Almighty to own your Highneſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, by many ſignall deliverances in Crowning your Highneſſe endeavours with ſo many renowned Victories. Upon whoſe Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious temper I have preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to preſent my weak en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours which containes that ſubject which King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> himſelfe thought neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be ſearcht into: And being the practiſe of ſo Holy a man as <hi>David,</hi> I hope may prove acceptable to your Highneſſe; into whoſe Clemencie and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:110887:4"/> I caſt my ſelfe, and all at your mercifull Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which if I were not in ſome meaſure aſſured of, the place where theſe labours had their Birth ſhould have been the place of their Buriall; neither ſhould they have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further then thoſe walls wherein they were Enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo have breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth their laſt where they had their firſt Being: Preſuming therefore on your Highneſſe, who is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Patron but Protector of the Truth: I ſhelter my poor labours under the
<pb facs="tcp:110887:4"/> wings of your Protection, deſiring a favourable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The leaſt and unworthieſt of yours and the Churches ſervants</hi> G. BURCHES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:110887:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110887:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not the thirſt of Vain glory that makes me run the hazzard of the worlds cenſure, neither am I fearfull of thoſe venemous reproaches which either malice or ignorance can lay unto my charge in expreſſing my labours to the publick view:<note place="margin">Quiquid reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur, recipitur ad modum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipientis.</note> I very well know Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and Trastates have their Dooms partly according to the capacities, partly according to the affections of the Readers and Hearers. Hence though ſome applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Chriſt, and ſaid he was a good
<pb facs="tcp:110887:6"/> man; others derided him and ſaid, he deceived the people. Its no ſtrange thing in this latter Age of the world to hear and ſee the most bitter invectives of malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tongues ſpit out to blemiſh the moſt innocent perſons.<note place="margin">Ne cibus ipſe juvat morſu fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datus aceti. Mar. Epigr.</note> The breath of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred turne the moſt wholeſome food into poyſon; and where the Bees (the Saints of God) gather Honey, the moſt hurtfull creatures, (malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons) conveigh all into poyſon and become banefull too. Theſe like <hi>Lamia</hi> that Witch in the Fable, whom <hi>Plutarch</hi> mentions, put on their eyes when they go abroad, are Eagle-ſighted in condemning their brethren: but lay them aſide when they come home,<note place="margin">Sentiant, dicant quid velint, dum mea me conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia non accuſat coram. Deo. Aug.</note> blind in perceiving their own faults.
<pb facs="tcp:110887:6"/> For my own part I paſſe not the Worlds cenſure, ſo long as I keep the peace of a good Conſcience, neither will I cenſure any that unjuſtly lies at my repu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; but rather will endeavour to requite their malice with forgiveneſſe, who one day may be made ſenſible of their own folly. And therefore all that I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ſay unto the Reader, ſhall be this, If thou proveſt judicious and learned, I reſpect and love thee; If Criticall and but ſimple, I ſlight thee: If mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and hateful, I pitty thee; If pious and charitable, I prize and honor thee: If Factious and Heretical, I have here preſcribed a remedie to cure the Crotchets and whimſies of thy brain and ſo farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:110887:7"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 11. l. 19. r. excellent. p. 22. l. 14. dele a. p. 25. l. 7. r. any one man. p. 30. l. 10. r. whole race. p. 37, l. 23. r. that <hi>Adam</hi> p. 56. l. 4. r. that is and dele. p. 76. l. 3. r. given. p. 85. l. 7. r. their for the. p. 81. l. 20. for and r. which. p. 82. l. 8. r. omit. p. 98. l. 14. r. Be not like hills the higher the barrenner, but like unto Diamonds, the bigger the better.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110887:7"/>
            <head>The Doctrine of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall ſinne main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 51.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Behold I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſinne did my mother conceive me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalm conteines a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Royall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets recovery, out of thoſe foul and damnable ſinns of Murther and Adultery: And it is an exact deſcription of Mans miſery and Gods mercy; ſhewing that as the one abounds, the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110887:8"/> other ſuperabounds, both exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in and upon the perſon of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid:</hi> evidently manifeſting and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, that as ſin had abounded by him, ſo the Grace of God unto him, and the power of Grace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him had abounded much more. And it may be divided into ſix parts, and reduced into ſix princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall heads, which may be called the degrees of true Converſion and Regeneration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt means of Converſion is the Grace of God, reproving the ſinner for his iniquity, and recalling him to repentance by the Miniſtry of the Prophets, the Preachers of his word, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Title of the Pſalm; <hi>To him that excelleth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The power of Faith ſignified by the Prophets ſubmiſſion thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, in the firſt and ſecond verſes. <hi>Have mercy upon my O Lord,</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110887:8"/> teaching us, that when we are reproved and convicted of ſin by the preaching of the Law, not to wax furious and diſcontent through impatience, or deſpair, but in meekneſſe and humility to ſeeke unto the Phycſiian; and humbly to preſent our ſelves at the feet of Gods mercy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Prophets ingenuous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the heinouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and hatefulneſſe of his ſin. <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>For I acknowledge my tranſgreſſion, and my ſin is ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Contrition, which is a curious ſearch and enquiry that he made into the ground and nature of his ſin. <hi>ver.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Hence the Prophet proceeds to the procuring of the remedy, or the Application of the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, which is the blood of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110887:9"/> Chriſt. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>Purge me with Hyſop and I ſhall be cleanſed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The perfection of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which by ſome is called ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, by others vivificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The power and practiſe of Religion conſiſting in holineſſe and newneſſe of life, ſet forth in the reſt of the Pſalm.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the waies wherein we muſt walk; theſe are the true meanes and works of Converſion: the want of any of which doth fruſtrate all our hopes, and makes all the reſt ineffectuall to us.</p>
            <p>Now if we make Examination and enquiry in which of theſe we are moſt defective: it will appear without all queſtion, to be that which of all other is moſt croſſe and troubleſom to fleſh and blood, moſt irkſom to nature; and is therefore moſt neglected of all ſorts of men, and that is true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110887:9"/> contrition, a diligent ſearch and inquiſition in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal ground and cauſes of our ſin, a thing of all other moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as being the chiefeſt and moſt principal part of repentance, the trueſt part of mortification, without the which, there can be no other certain aſſurance of Grace nor ſincerity of Religion. And therefore in ſurvey and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this Pſalm, I make choice to ſpeak of this ſubject before the reſt; as being by the ſtrange ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect and ignorance of men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the moſt needfull to be urged and preſſed upon the conſcience of all ſorts, that flatter and delude themſelves, only with a ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and ſhallow acquaintance and conformity with the external ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion, without any true power and practiſe thereof, the ſubject whereof is excellently,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110887:10"/> and ſubſtantially propoſed in the words of the Text, <hi>Behold I was ſhapen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Text give me leave to tearm</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mans inbred malady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The deſignation of the Prophets diſeaſe, the cauſe of the miſerie and complaint, the ſubject whereof he intendeth to ſpeak, in this particle, <hi>Behold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The diſeaſe it ſelf, ſet forth by theſe two words, <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The original ground from whence it ſprung, and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, intimated alſo in theſe words, <hi>Shaping,</hi> and <hi>Conceiving. Behold I was ſhapen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All of them affording both intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall inſtructions, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and alſo moral documents, for the reformation of our lives:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110887:10"/> the one teaching us what we are to know, the other directing us what we are to do; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of them all briefly in their order.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the deſignation of the Prophets diſeaſe, or the cauſe of his complaint: and ſurely it is ſuch a deſignation, as doth imply wonder, and therefore it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt with this particle of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>Behold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is a Doctrine ſtrange and obſcure, and of great difficulty, ſuch as few men truly know and underſtand, and fewer thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weigh and conſider. A Doctrine ſo full of depth, and alſo of ſuch neceſſity, that it requires moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious attention and conſideration; a Doctrine ſo grounded in truth, and likewiſe ſo full of terror, as of all other, it is moſt powerfull, and effectuall, to magnifie the juſtice
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110887:11"/> and mercy of God; as alſo to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the inſolence of the proud heart of man; and therefore it is intit'led and ſtiled with an <hi>Ecce, Behold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As indeed, whereſoever we find in ſcripture ſuch an inſcription, it ſhould prepare us to an expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of high myſteries, of matter of ſuch great conſequence, as doth expect from us our beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and diligence to know, and our willingneſſe and forward readineſs to obey, which is in this particular plainly verifyed.</p>
            <p>For in the whole courſe of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, there is no point, either more obſcure in it ſelfe to know, or more unpleaſing to our nature to learn; and yet nothing more profitable or behoofefull to our reformation, nothing more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be diſcuſſed for our edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: without the knowledge of which, all the reſt are in vain,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110887:11"/> it being the ground of all. The ſubject of his juſtice, and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy: The laſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple which the wiſe ſages of the world preſcribed unto their ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to ſtudie, and the firſt whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome document, which all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Prophets of God have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to their Diſciples.</p>
            <p>So that briefly having pointed out the diſeaſe whereof the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet complaines, let us in the next place ſet our eyes upon it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what it is, and wherein it doth conſiſt. <hi>Behold, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All things that are, both are in themſelves, and alſo demonſtrable what they are by their cauſes: thoſe principles, of which their nature and eſſence doth conſiſt, and whereby they are diſtinguiſhed from all other things; which things we cannot doe in demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating the nature of ſin, becauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110887:12"/> it is nothing: for every thing that hath any being or exiſtence in nature, was created by God; and all things that were created, were exceeding good. Whence it is, that <hi>Ens &amp; bonum</hi> are <hi>convertibilia.</hi> That every thing that hath a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is good, and every thing that is good, hath a being in it ſelfe. Since therefore being evil is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and of nothing there can be no cauſes propoſed, by which we may demonſtrate the ſame, ſo properly and exactly, as of things that have natural exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence and being in themſelves.</p>
            <p>And yet by the way, to prevent the ignorant miſtaking, whereunto vulgar conceits are ſubject, we are not to think, that, becauſe ſin is ſaid to be nothing, we are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſet light by it, and to eſteem it (as we ſay) as a thing of nothing. For there is a difference to be put
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110887:12"/> betwixt <hi>non ens et nihil.</hi> Between <hi>non ens privativum &amp; non ens ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativum.</hi> Between that nothing which is no being at all, and that which is only the privation of that good, which is in that which is good. As for example, there is a difference betwixt no eyes at all, which is nothing negatively, and blindneſſe which is nothing priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, which is nothing but the want of ſight in the eye; the one importing an utter vacuitie of any thing at all, the other deſtruction of that which hath a being: the privation of the goodneſſe of all things wherein it is, and the very blemiſhing and disfiguring of that eye-lent character of Beauty, which the wiſdome of God hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed upon the comely face of nature, as it was firſt created.</p>
            <p>Now in diſcovering of this, we are (I ſay) not able to make any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110887:13"/> certain demonſtration, becauſe there can be no certain and univocall cauſes preſcribed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: only we may analogically, by way of reſemblance, by reflecting our cogitations, and comparing ſin with the habit, whereof it is the privation, illuſtrate, and after a ſort demonſtrate the ſame. For <hi>cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitio privationis praeſupponit cognitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem habitus, et ſine ea acquiri non poteſt.</hi> The knowledge of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of any thing, doth preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the knowledge of that Habit whereof it is the privation: &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, it cannot be attained unto. It is therefore neceſſary, that in ſearching out of the knowledge of ſin, we compare it with righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, being that habit whereof ſin is the privation.</p>
            <p>To proceed therefore. <hi>Privatio et Habitus dicitur cicra idem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid,</hi> ſaith the Oracle of Nature,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110887:13"/> in his book of praedicaments. Both the privation and Habit, are converſant about the ſame thing or object. The object of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being the Law, it doth follow that the object of ſin is the Law alſo: but what Law? Both the Law of nature, which God had preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed unto every thing in nature to be obſerved by them, as being unto God moſt honorable, and to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt proper, and behoofe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Thoſe rules and limitations, thoſe orders and preſcriptions, which the wisdome of God had propoſed and imprinted upon all creatures: either of the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their being, or the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſexes, or the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their kinds, or the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their power and manner of working, or the manifeſtation of his own Almighty power, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and glory, the ſame are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110887:14"/> termed Lawes. So <hi>He made a Law for the rain,</hi> ſaid <hi>Job, Job.</hi> 2.8. <hi>And he gave a decree unto the Sea, that the waves ſhould not paſſe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</hi> And by this Law it is, that heavie bodies move down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, but light bodies aſcend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: that the motion of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are circular, and that every thing obſerves that manner of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and working, which is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and proper unto his kind.</p>
            <p>Now creatures having their ſeveral degrees of perfection, and Law being as it were the ſeveral rules and ſpurrs thereof; it will follow, The perſecter any creature is, the more general, and of larger excellency are thoſe Laws, by which the ſame is guided. So we ſee that Minerals are of a perfecter conſtitution and being, then ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bodies: as Air, or Water, or Earth, or Plants, are perfecter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110887:14"/> then Stones, and Beaſts are more perfect then Plants, and that Man is more perfect then all: So that every one of theſe in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall kinds, have more or leſſe notion &amp; motion belonging unto them, and accordingly are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to more or leſſe Laws.</p>
            <p>Now men being as it were a compendium or Epitome, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviature of all the creatures of God, and participating of all the perfections, hath ſo many actions and operations proper unto him, as makes him ſubject to all the lawes; not only to the part of natures law, that concerns only his reaſonable Soul and will, and is therefore called the morall Law, but likewiſe unto all the ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate parts, that may any waies concern his inferior parts and faculties: ſo that not only the Soul, the underſtanding, but the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110887:15"/> ſenſes and humors, yea the very whole proportion and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body, and every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular therein, had their ſeverall preſcriptions and motions peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar unto themſelves, which both for ability and power, and end, and all other circumſtances, they ought to have obſerved exactly, and could not tranſgreſſe without ſin.</p>
            <p>So that firſt hearing of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of ſin, namely, the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: That Law which Almighty God had preſcribed univerſally unto all things in nature to be obſerved, let us proceed unto the farther ſearch thereof: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ſecond place we ſay, that the form of righteouſneſſe, is the obſervation of this Law: and hence we inſert, <hi>tanquam formale peccati,</hi> that the tranſgreſſion of the law is as it were the form of ſin. For ſo 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. defineth that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110887:15"/> ſin is <hi>the tranſgreſſion of the Law,</hi> that it is an aberration and excur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion out of the bonds and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts of Gods Law, 1. <hi>John</hi> 3.4.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly, The materiall cauſes of Righteouſneſſe, were the actions and operations, faculties and parts of man; and therefore we muſt propoſe them alſo <hi>tanquam materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale peccati,</hi> as the matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of ſin: For look how the parts and faculties both of Soul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy were ordered, and framed, and beautified, and exerciſed in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe: So likewiſe the ſame parts and faculties both of Soul and body, are confuſed, diſtemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, deformed, and perverted by iniquity and ſin. For the efficient cauſe of righteouſneſſe being <hi>libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum arbitrium hominis,</hi> the free will of man; it muſt needs follow, that the efficient cauſe of ſin muſt needs be the ſame, or elſe could
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110887:16"/> not be ſaid to be our ſin; for that which makes a work to be our work, is, becauſe it proceeds from our own will: for ſin in the formes and abſtracted nature thereof, namely, as it is the tranſgreſsion of the Law, may be, and is, in beaſts, and other creatures, yet cannot be ſaid to be the ſin of the creature, becauſe it proceeds not from will in the creature; for the creature is <hi>ſubject to vanity,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20. Neither is it ſufficient to make a work ours, unleſſe it proceed freely from us, without any neceſsity compelling us unto: for then the act would be attributed as much, yea princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, to the neceſsity, and we ſhould be but as inſtruments there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: That therefore is the efficient of ſin unto man, which doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate ſin unto man, and that doth appropriate ſin unto him,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110887:16"/> which is the principal facultie by which he worketh, namely, <hi>Liberum Arbitrium,</hi> his free will.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the finall cauſe or effect of righteouſneſſe was joy, and peace, and comfort, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and perfection, and all the happineſſe which the ſoul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of man was capable of. So <hi>è contrario,</hi> for <hi>rectum eſt Index ſui &amp; obliqui:</hi> we moſt ſtill meaſure that which is crooked by that which is ſtreight, the final cauſe and effect of ſin is ſorrow, affliction, croſſes, and deſtruction, and all the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in this life, and in the life to come. For as <hi>malum culpae</hi> was the privation of <hi>bonum morale;</hi> ſo <hi>malum poenae</hi> is the privation of <hi>bonum delectabile.</hi> As ſin was the privation of righteouſneſſe, ſo effect of ſin is the privation of happineſſe, which is the fruit of righteouſneſſe: For all the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110887:17"/> and pains that hath or ſhal ever befal man, are no poſitive thing, but a meer privation of that goodneſſe which was created in him. As for example; If ſharp nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles ſhall be thruſt under the nails, it is nothing but the violent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and diſturbance of the frame of nature in thoſe parts. If our hands or feet ſhould be dipt in boyling lead; it were but the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent diſtemper of heat in theſe members; and ſo of other torments which are all privations. Neither did the eye ſee, nor hath ear heard, nor did ever poſsibly enter into the heart of man the joyes that are prepared for the righteous: All things in the world are too low to expreſſe them. So on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it will follow, that neither eye, nor ear, or heart, hath either ſeen, or can imagine thoſe pains that are prepared for ſinners; all things in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110887:17"/> this world are too ſhort to reſemble them.</p>
            <p>For as the choice and pretious ſtones mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. are there uſed to repreſent the new Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and the beauty and joyes thereof, which are far more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and of an higher, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent qualitie: So, under refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of better judgment, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that the fire, which the ſpirit of God in the Scripture makes choice of, to expreſſe the torments of Hel, is not material fire, but being the moſt violent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming element, is uſed only as the fitteſt thing to repreſent thoſe unconceivable pains: For I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe torments to be much more, then any fire can inflict: for the pains, afflictions, and croſſes of this life, are not to be ſpoken of, in reſpect of thoſe endleſs and infinite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orrowes in the life to come: That
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110887:18"/> we ſuffer here is but a miſerable paſſage to that we ſhal feel here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter, and rather to be counted bleſsings then croſſes, being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible means which God uſeth to humble us, and as bridles to check our unruly and headſtrong luſts; yea as wormwood to wean our appetites from the deſire of the worlds vanities: For howſoever many doe account themſelves hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py that live in eaſe and abundance here on earth, yet moſt certain it is, that there can be no greater a curſe or croſſe befal any man in this life, then to proſper in the courſe of ſin and iniquity.</p>
            <p>But to return from whence we digreſſed. The miſeries of ſin ſhall be farre greater then any thing in this world can reſemble, when as by the power and juſt Iudgment of God, there ſhal be ſuch exact and exquiſite diſtemper and pains in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110887:18"/> upon every part and parcell of man, that if all the moſt forcible torments that ever were invented by the moſt cruel Tyrants that ever lived were put together, they were as nothing in reſpect of thoſe infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite pains and tortures which man ſhal everlaſtingly ſuffer in hell: where the humors ſhal be both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed &amp; benumed, with unſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heat &amp; cold; where the ſenſes are infected with moſt loathſome and abominable ſtenches and ſavours; their eyes terrified with gaſtly and fearfull ſpectacles; when the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſhal find no refreſhing, but endleſſe grief and afflictions, when every joynt ſhall be diſordered and racked <hi>in extenſum</hi> as poſſibly it can bear; when the glandules, the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and all the fleſhie parts ſhal frie in ſcorching heat, where the entrals and bowels ſhall perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gnaw with continuall griping;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110887:19"/> yea, when theſe ſhall be filled with everlaſting anguiſh and horror, by being baniſhed for ever from the preſence of almighty God, and the communion of his bleſſed Saints and Angels, and inſtead thereof aſtoniſhed with the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and hideous noiſe and wailing of wretched ſouls, never to ſee hope for eaſe or end of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable miſeries. And laſtly, when thoſe carnifices, thoſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned executioners of Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Divels, being caſt down from the glorious preſence of God's Almightie Majeſty, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the infinite and unſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burthen of his juſtly deſerved wrath and anger, ſhal execute their unſpeakable malice and furious vengeance upon the miſerable bodies, and diſtreſſed Soules of reprobate and condemned ſinners. Nay, to conclude, if all their griefs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110887:19"/> and diſeaſes, all the anguiſh of mind whereunto the body and ſoul of men are ſubject, and, which all the men, from the beginning of the world unto this day have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, were in the extremity upon any other man; and that the ſoules and bodies by the Almighty power of God were ſo faſtned together, and ſo perpetually conjoyned, that there could be no diſſolution, yet all this muſt the ſinner eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endure, beſides infinitely more ſorrowes and pains, all unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, all unconceivable. Hence from the cauſes, we define the ſin that it is</p>
            <p>A determinate and wilful tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of Gods Law, depriving all the parts and faculties both of Soule and body, of all kind of goodneſſe, of all kind of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe in it ſelf, &amp; of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of happineſſe, which had
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110887:20"/> been the effect and conſequent thereof.</p>
            <p>So that having pointed out the diſeaſe, and conſidered what it is, it remaines in the laſt place to ſearch out the Original ground, whence it ſprings, and proceeds, intimated in theſe words [<hi>ſhaping,</hi> and <hi>conceiving] Behold I was ſhapen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peccato Originali</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aug.) nihil ad praedicandum notius, nihil ad intelligendum ſecretius.</hi> There's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more commonly preached, and yet nothing more obſcurely to be underſtood, then Original ſin. And iniquitie is a myſterie (ſaies the Scripture) neither of which doth imply an impoſſibilitie, but only a difficulty of underſtanding the depth and ſecrets thereof: and therefore, as the ſearch of the knowledge thereof requires deeper ſpeculation; ſo doth the delivery
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110887:20"/> thereof, deſerve more heedful, and ſerious attention. <hi>I was ſhapen in iniquitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may not now ſtand to diſpute that queſtion, which is diſputed in the works of ſome great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines; namely, whether propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and traducing of ſin be from the Father or Mother: Some col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting and affirming from that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>As by one man ſin entered into the world, &amp;c.</hi> that ſin procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only, and is derived from the man, and if the woman could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and bring forth without the man, the child be without ſin. Others again inſerting that, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>That the man was not deceived but the woman was, and was in the tranſgreſſion:</hi> And alſo from this of the Prophet in the Text, <hi>In ſin hath my Mother conceived me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inferring, I ſay, that it is proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that ſin is principally derived
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110887:21"/> from the Mother; which queſtion may eaſily be decided, by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging it both waies. True, that it deſcends from the man and the woman; for under that phraſe, <hi>as by one man,</hi> may be well implyed both ſexes; and certain it is, that both being Parents, and both ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, they are as well the parents of the ſin as of the child.</p>
            <p>But to return to our purpoſe, <hi>I was ſhapen in iniquitie,</hi> ſaies the Prophet, declaring thereby the original ground and cauſe of this diſeaſe, the manner how it became ſinful; wherein it may be proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly objected, that in as much as the principal guilt of ſin depends upon the efficient cauſe thereof; namely, <hi>Liberum arbitrium homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> the freewill of man, in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſobedience of Gods Law, which <hi>David</hi> never had, but was born, as all other men, captives to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110887:21"/> their luſts, and could not obey the Law, if he had been never ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and which never man had, but one: Neither was ſin in that extenſe and high nature, which the free and malitious a verſion of the will perpetrated and committed by any one, but by that one; and that by a tranſient act many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years afore: how then can the Prophet be ſaid to be guilty of ſin in that kind, which onely proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; <hi>undequaque</hi> completly is ſin, or juſtly aſſum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the laſt unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the act of our firſt parents was tranſient, yet the will of that act was permanent, and remaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and it is juſtly reputed unto the Prophet and unto all men that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from their loyns. It ſtanding both with the rule of equitie and righteous judgment, juſtly to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110887:22"/> and impute that unto us, which we as it were did in our progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: for can any man be more juſt and equal, then to charge every part by that which is committed by the whole; for all the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſucceſſions of men make but one body, and every one is member of that body: and the whole leaſe of man is but as one tree, whereof our firſt parents are the root, and therefore that ſprig which hath but newly ſprouted out this year, proceeds Originally (though by the mediation of the body and branches of that root, which may be was planted many hundred years agoe) If the root be corrupt, ſtruck, and die, it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe corrupt, ſtrucken and dies with it; and why? becauſe it is a part of that body that is of the ſame nature, qualitie, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the root: Even ſo it is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110887:22"/> with all men that both have been, and now are born, they lineally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, &amp; by the mediation of the body, the generations and ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, they proceed from the firſt parent of mankind, as from the root, they participate of his nature, qualities, and properties, and therefore if his condition be ſinful, damnable, their's likewiſe is ſinful, damnable; becauſe the guilt of what he did is juſtly imputed unto them, as being then with him; and now deſcending from his loyns; and that according to the rule of natures Law, according to the equitie of divine juſtice: all the ſpecies, the whole kind of man were potentially in <hi>Adam,</hi> and by right of inheritance from ſin, are intituled to the priviledges of nature; whatſoever belonged to him, they may juſtly challenge; that is, all kind of ſuſtenance for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110887:23"/> the preſervation of their being: as nature hath given unto us a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo it owes unto us a ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; ſhall we challenge God for maintenance and preſervation of life, in right of our firſt parents? &amp; ſhall not he as juſtly challenge us as guilty of ſin, &amp; ſubject to his wrath, &amp; deſcending from him who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſgreſſed &amp; diſobeyed his Law? ſhal we not partake of the good and evil whereunto we are intituled in right of our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents? ſurely both alike belongeth unto us; and therefore even in our conception, when we as it were firſt ſprout out, even then are we juſtly accounted guilty of wilfull diſobedience and ſin, becauſe we deſcend from the loins of him that did wilfully diſobey and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the Law of his mighty Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator: So that all excuſe by juſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation hereof being taken away,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110887:23"/> by this means ſin being appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated unto us, we made guilty thereof in the higheſt degree, as proceeding from the intent diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the reaſonable will.</p>
            <p>Let us proceed to conſider out of the Prophets words, the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of ſin, when, after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or in what meaſure we are made ſinful, hence implyed in this word, <hi>Mother;</hi> that is, from the very act of generation; for the firſt, ſhe takes upon her the office of <hi>Mother,</hi> after what manner ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in theſe two words, <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,</hi> and <hi>conceiving;</hi> and laſtly, in what meaſure, implyed in this particle, <hi>I;</hi> that is, not this, or that part of me, but <hi>I</hi> wholly; that is every part and faculty in me.</p>
            <p>In the former clauſe, namely; of the guilt of the imputation of our firſt parents ſin, we ſpeak of ſin only in relation to the efficient
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110887:24"/> cauſe, who did it, and how it was actual: In this we conſider ſin in the form thereof, namely, as it tranſgreſſeth the law, how it is originally diffuſed over every part and faculty of us, and ſo it becomes habitual, <hi>I was ſhapen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>ſhaping</hi> is underſtood the firſt framing and faſhioning of us in the womb; and by <hi>conceiving</hi> is meant the firſt being and breeding and growing up unto perfection in the womb: for <hi>Tremel.</hi> tranſlats it, <hi>in peccando fovet me mea Mater, In ſin hath my Mother cherished me up.</hi> And ſo is our Hebraiſme in our Engliſh margent: <hi>In ſin did my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther warm me,</hi> which implyeth the ſame thing; both importing, that man both in his firſt beginning, &amp;- alſo in his continual grouth &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, is ſinful, that is, every way exceeding ſinfull. If a man ſhould be born, having his face ſtanding
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110887:24"/> backward, and his legs coming out where his armes ſhould be, and his armes out of his belly, and his belly upon his head, it would ſurely be eſteemed an ugly mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, fearful, and prodigious; and yet the deformity and obliquity of the Soul and body of man by ſin, is much more monſtrous, where every part and faculty is diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; where every particular is both <hi>extra</hi> and <hi>praeter intentionem naturae;</hi> both beſides and beyond the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature, as by the ſequel ſhall appear.</p>
            <p>Now perfect and compleat <hi>ſhaping</hi> doth imply two ſeveral acts: Firſt, the exact temperature of internal qualities: 2ly, the due proportion of the externall parts and lineaments; In both theſe there is ſin formally, which is the tranſgreſsion of the law. For God, in the creation, had ſet down a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110887:25"/> law alſo for things of this inferior quality and reſpect, which could not be tranſgreſſed without ſin; in the firſt place preſcribing unto every thing ſuch a juſt and limited temper and mixture of primari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> qualities of heat and cold, of drie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and moiſture, whereof all mixt bodies conſiſt, and was moſt behoofeful to the perfection and preſervation of his being: and Secondly, ſquaring out ſuch a due and excellent proportion and faſhion in all the body, as might beſt adorn it with moſt beautie and comlineſſe, thereby ſo manifeſting his power and wiſdome in all things, that there was neither diſtemper inwardly, nor defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie outwardly in any thing that he hath made.</p>
            <p>Both theſe laws are broken and tranſgreſſed in the ſhaping of men.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:110887:25"/>
            <p>For firſt, there is ſuch a diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of ſuch unequal iniquity of the radical heat and radical moiſture, which are <hi>principia vitae,</hi> as the Phyſicians call them, the very principles and grounds of life; that the healthieſt man living is not perfectly in health, though yet not ſenſibly and throughly ſick, but lives as it were in a neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality betwixt both, yet rather ſick then wel, becauſe the diſeaſe is ſtill growing, though not ripe, until the diſtemper thereof wax ſo ſtrong and predominant, that nature is ſo weakened and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued thereby, that it is not able without grief to reſiſt the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, In the outward framing and faſhioning of the body, there is no man that hath that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act proportion and comelineſſe in the parts of the body, then <hi>Adam</hi> had that was immediately created
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110887:26"/> by God, but there is in it ſome imperfection or blemiſh, which doth ſome way either di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>figure or deform him: Nay, I will ſay that, which many perhaps will think ſtrange, that there is not in us the leaſt joynt, but ſin is in it, not only formally, as there is a want of perfection in the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conſtitution thereof, according to the law of God, but alſo imputatively, becauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo by the rebellion of our will, that thereby we have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the law, defaced the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of God within us, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived our ſelves of health and perfection, and ſo juſtly become the ſubjects of Gods vengeance. Nay, I will ſay more, that there is no grief nor pain that the beaſts or other creatures in the world do ſuffer, but it is ſin formally, a tranſgreſſion of this Law. Becauſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110887:26"/> God intended no ſuch affliction to any of his creatures by the Creation, but by his Law both eſtabliſhed it and ordained it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, that namely, the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhould live in that perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and happineſſe, whereof by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they were capable. There is no imperfection in any creature but man is guilty thereof, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by his ſin: For <hi>curſed is the earth and all things therein for mans ſake:</hi> and why for mans ſake? but for ſin; and what is that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? but the ſubſtraction and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation of the Lords prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and guidance of the creatures in the lawes and rules of natures law. Rightly therefore ſaies the Prophet, <hi>I was ſhapen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not only therein doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the whole ground and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal cauſe of his diſeaſe, but he adds alſo, that in ſin his Mother
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110887:27"/> warmed and cheriſhed him up, both root and branches were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. In conſideration whereof it will appear, that as the ſtructure and compoſition of man is moſt admirable, ſo the corruption of ſin in man is moſt damnable, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a general diſturbance of the whole courſe of nature, a peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent infection univerſally diffuſed over all the faculties both of Soul and body.</p>
            <p>For as nature hath ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of perfection, and ſtill the former is the ground of the latter, ſo alſo have theſe degrees their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of infection; and ſtill the latter is enforced by the former.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt degree of natural per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in man is <hi>eſſe,</hi> conſiſting in the conſtitution and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature of the body, which is the ground of all motions and life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is <hi>Vegetare,</hi> by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110887:27"/> nouriſhment to encreaſe, and grow to perfection in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is <hi>Sentire,</hi> an abilitie to diſcern and know all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and corporeal objects, and their ſimple qualities.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth is <hi>ratiocinari,</hi> by diſcourſe of reaſon, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of outward things, and to draw out ſuch rules and directions for this life as are conſonant to that law which God had eſtabliſhed in all things.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Secundum rationem agere,</hi> to work and frame all his actions according to their deſtinated ends: namely, the preſervation of natures perfection, and the glory of natures God.</p>
            <p>Now as theſe degrees of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perfection have their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance the one upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110887:28"/> in their order; ſo likewiſe in the infection and diffuſion of ſin upon the natural qualities, do the vital faculties depend upon the vital, the animal upon the animal, the rationall upon the rational, the moral, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt; if there be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate mixture of cold and heat in the natural conſtitution, as hath been declared there is, then do the vital faculties fail in the exerciſe of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir functions; as too much heat doth inflame the blood, encreaſe choler, drie the braine; too much cold doth beget melancholy, augment flegme, hinder digeſtion, dul the ſpirits, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the vital faculties be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, the animal are diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereby: as the over abundance of ill humors doth ſend up noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and unwholeſome fumes into
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110887:28"/> the head, which do ſtupifie the ſenſe, dul the imagination, and hurt the memory, ſo that if the fantaſie and memory be any way impaired, then in the third place, the reaſonable ſoul is greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled in the exerciſe of her facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, if reaſon be abſurd and defect, in that it is not able to direct, how then can the will exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute or perform any thing that is agreeable to Gods Law?</p>
            <p>Behold how great a flame a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fire kindleth, for the natural temperature of the firſt qualities heat and cold, &amp;c. though in mens ordinary imaginations, they are things of ſmall moment or reſpect; and nothing ſo material and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, as the ſuperior faculties; yet are they ſo neceſſary, and of ſuch force in the whole frame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of man, that upon their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110887:29"/> goodn ſſe doth the goodneſſe of all the reſt depend, no otherwiſe then as the ſpring or poize in a curious clock, which ſeems to be dull and of no great neceſſity, and yet it is of the greateſt power, as that which moves all the reſt of the wheels: for the perfection of a clock is to keep its time and due howers; but if the ſpring or poize be diſordered, all the reſt is diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, if it be too ſtrong, then the howers are too ſhort, and if ſlack and looſe, then are they too long. So the natural faculties, if too cold, then all the reſt are d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtitute and too remiſs; if tooo hot, then are they too violent and redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant; for the diſpoſition and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Soules working, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth principally upon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies temperature. For as the eye, the <hi>int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmedium,</hi> that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed betwixt the eye and the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110887:29"/> object be thick, as in a miſt, it is obſcured, and the ſight made im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect: So the Soul, if the Organs, thoſe inſtruments by which it works, be diſordered and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, is diſabled in the exerciſe and uſe of its faculties. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, we ſee in a drunken man, when the ſtomach is oppreſſed with a thick and ſtrong moiſture, the heat of the liver by concoction, and digeſtion rarifies the ſame, there riſeth ſuch a fume, no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then we ſee in a boyling pot, which aſcending up into the head, doth ſo ſtupifie and diſtemper the brain, the Organ of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, imagination and diſcourſe; that man thereby that diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers himſelfe, doth quite loſe the uſe of his reaſon, and the chief faculty of his ſoul, and becomes for the time, (if not worſe) even a very beaſt. Even ſo every man
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110887:30"/> by the diſtempered mixture of corrupted nature, is made either more or leſſe defective in the uſe of the ſoules vigour and power, by how much more or leſſe the inſtruments and organs, by which the ſoul worketh, are polluted, and diſtempered.</p>
            <p>From hence it is we ſee, that ſome men are more quick and active of apprehenſion and conceit; others likewiſe are ſtupid and of duller capacity, which only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the good or evil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the parts of the body; yea the very beſt and pureſt that is begotten by the corrupt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of man, is infinitely farre ſhort of that puritie and quickneſſe of capacitie which man by his creation naturally was endued withall.</p>
            <p>From hence therefore may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the vanity of the Pelagians
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110887:30"/> arguments, intending to prove that ſin is only learned by imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, becauſe the body cannot work upon the Soul which is a Spirit; for though the bodie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not work upon the ſubſtance of the ſoul, yet can it hinder and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the operations of the Soul, which it is to perform in and by the body; for by the bodies cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and diſordered diſtemper, there is either irregularity or iniquity in the manner, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and ataxie in the order; but eſpecially exceſſe or defect in them, ſure of every facultie of and action of man. As for example, if we ſurvey ſome particulars; and firſt in thoſe faculties which are called concupiſcibles, as hunger, a natural appetite to create for ſuſtenance and preſervation of life and being, cannot doe it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin; not that the deſire of meat
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110887:31"/> or action of eating is ſinfull, for it is natural, and all that is natural is good, as being the work of God; but the irregularitie and diſorder of the deſire and act is ſin; either we eat too much, or are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with that which will ſuffice nature, or deſire that which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſome, or loath that which would beſt nouriſh us, or in ſome meaſure and degree or other of gluttony; the law, that is, thoſe rules and limitations, which God had preſcribed in nature unto that facultie, is tranſgreſſed: So thirſt becomes drunkenneſſe, and that ſame <hi>cupiditas venerea</hi> is changed into luſt, and ſo by exceſſe is made ſloth; and ſo of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider the faculties called <hi>Iraſcibiles,</hi> and there we ſee that joy by exceſſe is turned into voluptuouſneſſe, and ſorrow into anxiety, that fear becomes hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110887:31"/> and anger is turned into fury, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd hatred into malice.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Proceed we unto the reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faculties, and ſee how hope exceeds by preſumption, how mercy becomes fooliſh pitty, how zeal runs into ſuperſtition, and knowledge into hereſie, and ſo of all the faculties of man.</p>
            <p>Neither do theſe only tranſgreſſe the law of God, by exceeding their limits and preſcriptions, but alſo being defective in the meaſure and intention thereof; ſo fear offends by ſecurity, and anger by ſtupidity, ſo hope oftentimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes deſpair, and mercy is turned into crueltie; ſo the defect of zeal is dulneſſe of ſpirit, and the defect of knowledge is ignorance; ſo of all the reſt which I may not now enumerate, their inordinate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the tranſgreſſion of the law, either on the right hand or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110887:32"/> on the left, either in exceſſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of their functions and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: ſo vertue conſiſts in <hi>medio,</hi> as it is in the mean between them: of the moderation of theſe exceſſes and the ſupplies of theſe deſires are called vertues or graces by their ſeveral effidients, vertues by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts, in ſo much as by educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and by the light and ſtrength of nature, they are in ſome meaſure corrected: and graces by Divines, becauſe by the power of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſpirit they are reformed.</p>
            <p>So that to draw all into a ſum, we may reduce Original ſin unto theſe three h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reatus inobedient to,</hi> guiltineſſe of diſobedience againſt Gods law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Defectus boni,</hi> a defect or w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all goodneſſe in our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Proclivitas ad malum,</hi> an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto wickedneſſe in all things we go about to do.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:110887:32"/>
            <p>The firſt in reſpect of the time paſt, the ſecond or the time preſent, and the third of the time to come. The one by imputation, the other by inhaeſion, the laſt by inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Being in the firſt place made guilty of ſin by the juſt imputation of the willfull diſobedience of our firſt Parents, becauſe we were then in their loins as parts of them, that now deſcend from them and ſprung out of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Being thereby made deficient, and deprived of all righteouſneſſe which God had created in us, and that happineſſe that was intended for us.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, being then wickedly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, there being in every part of us as well inferior of the body, as ſuperior of the ſoul, a diſpoſition or propenſity, an inclination or procli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity to erre from the rules of Gods Law; wherby we our ſelves every one of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110887:33"/> us, ſhall effect or bring to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our own finall overthrow or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, unleſſe by the mercy of God it be prevented.</p>
            <p>This is the Cataſtrophe, this is the univerſall Corruption, and ſubverſion of man: being every way ſinfull, both in <hi>Semine,</hi> in <hi>Embrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> and in <hi>Homine.</hi> Sinfull in his Conception and ſhaping, ſinfull in his growth and encreaſing, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſinfull in his ſtrength and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of being: and that not in any mean or remiſſe degree, but in every one of theſe, ſin being out of meaſure ſinfull. All this and much more then this was the ſorrowfull and penitent ſoul of the Prophet ſtrongly poſſeſt and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with all, in his deep medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſin in this place. Where he ſaith, <hi>I was ſhapen in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and in ſin did my mother conceive me.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:110887:33"/>
            <p>And thus having briefly run o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the matter, and unfolded the ſcope and ſenſe of the Text, as well as my underſtanding would ſerve: and therein propounded onely mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Inſtruction, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of our underſtanding, teaching us what we are to know. It remains in the next place, that we collect out of the precedent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſuch morall documents for the reformation of our lives, as may direct us what we are to do. Out of which, though I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve many, yet I will pitch my thoughts onely upon thoſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the deareſt Saints ſo well as the greateſt ſinners are in their Infancy Originally ſinfull.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the ſin which we are from our very infancy ſtained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, is conveyed by our Parents unto us.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:110887:34"/>
            <p>Concerning the firſt Truth, you have it here confirmed by the confeſſion of one that is recorded to be a man after Gods own heart, and thereby reputed to be a moſt dear Saint; yet for all that pleads not immunity from ſin in his very infancie, but ſaith, <hi>that he was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did his mother conceive him.</hi> Of the ſame mind with <hi>David</hi> the Father, was <hi>Solomon</hi> the Son. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.15. where he laies it down as an undeniable Axiome. <hi>That fooliſhneſſe is bound up in the heart of a child.</hi> By which phraſe is meant nothing but wickedneſſe and finn, which is on a child as a fardle or pack on a horſe back, which he can never of himſelf ſhake off. And this is the ground why the Lord himſelf ſpeaketh of the whole Nation of the Jewes which were then the onely Church hee had in the world. <hi>Eſay</hi> 48.8. <hi>Thou
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110887:34"/> waſt called a tranſgreſſor from the womb.</hi> Though they were a people in Covenant with God, yet in their infancy, in the womb a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor, yea, out of the womb ſo viſibly before Circumciſion tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors alſo. According to that of Saint <hi>Paul Eph.</hi> 2.3. <hi>We are all by nature the children of wrath as wel as others.</hi> Though the choſen of God, yet herein can plead no more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge from the exemption of this inbred pollution then <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf could, whom our Saviour calls no leſſe then a Devill. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44. <hi>Have not I choſen twelve, and one of them is a Devill.</hi> Hence is that of <hi>Aug. damnati antequam na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</hi> And therefore by ſome, Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſin is concluded to be not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a privation, but a corrupt habit, like unto a diſeaſe, which beſide the privation of health hath <hi>humores malé diſpoſitos,</hi> the humors ill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110887:35"/> whence it cometh to paſſe, <hi>that the imagination of mans heart</hi> (as the Lord ſpeaks, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.21.) <hi>vs evill from his very youth,</hi> there is a nature prone. There is in him a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall proneſſe, and diſpoſition to every thing that is evill: as there is in the youngeſt whelp of a Lion, or Bear, or a Woolfe to cruelty; or in the very egge of a Cockatrice before it be hatched: which is the compariſon which the Holy Ghoſt uſeth. <hi>Eſay</hi> 59.5. whereupon ſaies <hi>Aug. Concupiſcentia lex peccati cum parvulis naſcitur.</hi> Concupiſcence which is the Law of ſinne, is even born with Children. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies as much, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. <hi>I know that in me</hi> (that is, in my fleſh) <hi>dwelleth no good thing.</hi> And 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>We are not ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves: but our ſuffiencie is of God.</hi> The reaſons of which Doctrine are theſe.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:110887:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> 1. Becauſe of that guilt which Infants ſtand in <hi>Adam;</hi> In whom ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. (for ſo is that place rendred) <hi>all have ſinned.</hi> For <hi>Adam</hi> was not then as one particular perſon, but as the Common ſtock and root of all mankind: Whereupon by this ſin, all his poſterity which had been in ſin as in the root becomes equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinfull. Hence is that of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.18. <hi>A corrupt tree cannot bring forth good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruit.</hi> And he gives the reaſon, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Becauſe that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh:</hi> (that is, of the corrupt Parents) <hi>is ſinfull;</hi> which is <hi>Jobs</hi> meaning, where he ſaith, <hi>no man can beget a child that is clean from ſin, himſelf being unclean.</hi> This treaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by <hi>Adam</hi> runs through the whole blood: this leaven infecteth the whole lump: this poiſon is diffuſed into all mankind. And
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110887:36"/> ſince it comes to paſſe that man is diſabled from acting that which is good. For wee know that water can riſe no higher then the Fountain is; Nature will give it leave to go no higher: the fire giveth heat onely within a certain compaſſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and no farther. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can work beyond the ſphere of its own reach and activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. So it is impoſſible to corrupt nature, to elevate it ſelf to ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall grace; or to do any action preparing, bending, or inclining the will to it. For as water being cold by nature, cannot be made hot until an higher principle be firſt inſuſed into it: no more can mere nature do any thing tending to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace, untill it be raiſed up by an higher influence. For the guilt of <hi>Adams</hi> offence lies heavie upon all his poſterity, ſo that there being not left ſtrength in them as of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110887:36"/> themſelves to remove it, it diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles them from either thinking or acting any thing that is good, and though they may be Saints, yet in their Infancy are not freed from ſin: and therefore the ſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy it ſelfe hath been ſeverely puniſhed, as appears, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3. God commanded <hi>Saul</hi> to ſlay the very Infants and Sucklings of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and forbad to ſpare or ſhew pitty unto any of them: And <hi>Pſalms</hi> 137.9. the Lord pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him happy that ſhall take the little ones of the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> and daſh out their brains againſt the ſtones: And <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.25. we ſhall find, that in the deſtruction of <hi>Sodom,</hi> none of the inhabitants were ſpared, no not the Infants and ſucklings, but God rained down fire and brimſtone upon them: The like you ſhal find <hi>Numb.</hi> 16, 27. where from the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110887:37"/> it is ſaid, that <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biram</hi> came out, and ſtood in the doore of their Tents, and their wives and their ſons and their little children; all which were ſwallowed up by the earth, <hi>ver.</hi> 32. as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, and ſo went down quick into the pit. Now there can be no puniſhment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, but where ſin is preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, neither can there be any ſin in Infants thought on, but what is originally in their natures; and therefore to cleer the juſtice of God in puniſhing, the Doctrine of the Text is evident, that being originally ſinful, they ſuffer moſt juſtly by the hand of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But theſe be moſt lewd men, and God forbid but that there ſhould be a difference betwixt them and the godly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Infant of the beſt Chriſtian is by nature no better
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110887:37"/> then the infant of a Sodomite, as appears, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.3. and the ſin thoſe Infants was guilty of was the cauſe why God did thus deal with them: for <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>God is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter of perſons,</hi> and therefore hates ſin as well in them as in us; for hath not the infants of Gods own people been born fools natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, or deaf, or blind, as we may ſee, <hi>John</hi> 9.1. hath not many of them been ſmitten with many and grievous and ſtrange diſeaſes, as <hi>Davids</hi> child was, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.15. And what is this but a witneſſing of Gods wrath againſt them as well as others; for how can a moſt pure God love any thing that is polluted? This is contrary to his nature, <hi>whoſe pure eyes cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold iniquity:</hi> and therefore it is as eaſie for light and darkneſſe to agree together, as the moſt pure Creator, and impure creature to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110887:38"/> love each other. This I ſpeak not to abridge Gods mercy, how in his favour he may look upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants in his Son, but how God in himſelfe may behold them in their original ſin, being children of wrath, and ſo may become the fit objects of his wrath, to be ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed with their Parents.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, Becauſe of that filth which is conveyed from their Parents unto them: And therefore by <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.8. are ſaid to be <hi>tranſgreſſors from the womb: whoſe hearts are evil from their very youth, Gen.</hi> 8.11. Hence is that of <hi>Ambroſe, who is juſt in the ſight of God, whereas an Infant of a day old cannot be clear from ſin?</hi> every thing that is born, carrieth with it the nature of that which bare it, as touching the ſubſtance and accidents proper to that ſpeciall kind: But we are all born of corrupt and guilty pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110887:38"/> hence by nature in our birth we draw their guilt and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by this means we have the ſpawn and ſeed of all ſin within us, ſo that every imagination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes evil, only evil, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually evil, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6. as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſets us out in our natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> The 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the faithful are ſaid to be holy, therefore without Original ſin and pollution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They have not this Holineſs from carnal propagation, for it is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11.13. when they had neither done good nor evil, <hi>I have loved Jacob, and hated Eſau.</hi> But they are ſaid to be holy, in reſpect of the external fellowſhip of the Church; that is to ſay, they are to be accounted members of that body, the Church, whereof Chriſt is the head: and ſo alſo for the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110887:39"/> choſen and ſanctified of God, which place doth not any way infringe or prejudice this truth, for the natures of the beſt mens children are ſinful, though their perſons in reſpect of the external fellowſhip of the Church be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted holy, &amp; therefore Parents by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture derive not unto their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie righteouſneſs, which is free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imputed, but unrighteouſneſſe and damnation, unto which themſelves by nature are ſubject: and the reaſon is this, becauſe their poſteritie are not born of them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to grace, but according to nature; neither is grace and juſtification tyed to carnal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation, but to the moſt free election of God; ſo that though Infants be by the Apoſtle ſaid to be holy, yet it is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in reſpect of their natures, for that appears to be ſinful and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:110887:39"/> filthy, but in regard of that ſtipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and covenant which is made between God and the faithful: and therefore concludes nothing againſt this truth, but that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of the deareſt Saints are ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally ſinful.</p>
            <p>R. 3. Becauſe Children are deprived of thoſe ſupernaturall gifts and endowments, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they ſhould thorough <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> have poſſeſt, if hee had ſtood firm to his God. It's true, at the firſt when man was created, it was no ſmall part of his happineſſe in that primary condition to be ignorant of ſin, though a Quidditative knowledge perchance of the nature of ſin, he had by reaſon of the Law writ in his heart: yet a practicall experimentall knowledge he had not, he could not have; the miſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen brat of ſin being then unbegot, it was a meer <hi>Chimaera,</hi> an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110887:40"/> Monſter, having no Exiſtence but in Satans braine, the ſhop and forge of Hell. But alas this happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being but a dream of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of ſmall continuance through mens ambition; he is forthwith ſtript of it, and ſo becomes not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſpectacle of miſery himſelf, but makes his whole poſterity mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable alſo: So that what he acted, we in him became equally guilty and liable to the ſame wrath. For ſo ſaies the Apoſtle. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.14. In him we are, have ſinned, that is, in <hi>Adam, and are by nature the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath:</hi> wofull ſpectacles of wrath ſtript of al thoſe excellencies and gifts which in him wee might have enjoyed had he proved obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the command of his God. But being a wretched progenitor, begets a miſerable progenie, whoſe blood is ſo ſtained with his treaſon, as that they have forfeited all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110887:40"/> gifts and endowments through him: and though by the grace of Chriſt, reſtauration in ſome meaſure may he made to the Saints; yet are their Infants not freed from this inbred maladie, but are by nature originally ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj. Ezek</hi> 18 20. <hi>The Son ſhall not bear the iniquity of the Father. Ergo</hi> Injuſtice that <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity ſhould ſuffer for <hi>Adams</hi> ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's true, if he falls not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame, and approves it not, but diſliketh and avoideth it. But we juſtly bear the iniquity of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the fault is ſo <hi>Adams</hi> that it alſo becomes ours: For the Apoſtle witneſseth, <hi>We all ſinned in him: and ſo his ſin becomes ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe <hi>Adams</hi> whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nature was guilty, and we being as part proceeding out of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110887:41"/> and maſſe, we cannot but be guilty alſo our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> received the gifts of God to be imparted unto us on that condition, if him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did retain them: or loſe them unto us if himſelf loſt them: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as then <hi>Adam</hi> loſt them, he loſt them not onely in himſelf, but in all his poſterity alſo. So that hence it came to paſſe, that all thoſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall gifts and endowments which he had, we are deprived of, by reaſon of his falling from God.</p>
            <p>R. 4. Becauſe Originall ſin is <hi>peccatum hominis,</hi> a ſin of the whole man; whereupon this infection is conveyed by conjunction of both, they jointly making one man, enter into one condition, and ſo are partakers of each others woe or welfare. For though the ſoul comes immediately from God, and ſo is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110887:41"/> a pure ſubſtance: and the body can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſinfull without the ſoul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a dead maſſe, yet as <hi>peccatum hominis,</hi> the ſin of the whole mans infection is conveyed by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of both.</p>
            <p>Neither doth this infringe the Iuſtice of God, whatſoever ſome may ſay to the contrary, to thruſt a poor ſoul into an unclean bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. For the ſoul and body are not of God reſpected as ſingle ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but as they are joyned together to make one man, and therefore there is but one Conſtitution of both. The ſoul in reſpect of Gods creation is a pure Creature, yet it continueth not in that eſtate one moment, for it is created in the midſt of the body in an unclean and polluted place; and forthwith being coupled to the body, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be unclean. As a clear water caſt into a muddy place becomes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110887:42"/> ſuddenly foul. So doth the ſoul when united to the body, becomes ſuddenly ſinfull. Or as ſweet Oyle powred into a fuſtie veſſell, loſeth its pureneſſe. So the ſoul infuſed into the body, becometh impure and ſinfull. The pure ſoul is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the contagion of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure ſeed, as a fair flower is ſulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with unclean hands. Hence Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſin is ſaid to be, <hi>ex carne Cauſaliter,</hi> yet is in the ſoul <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective &amp; formaliter.</hi> And ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming <hi>peccatum hominis,</hi> the ſin of the whole man. The Infants of the beſt become Originally ſinfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. Seeing Infants are origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſinful, this may ſerve in the firſt place, to confute that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Pelagians, who deny that ſin cometh by nature, but is learned only by example or imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which if this could be, I would gladly know by what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110887:42"/> did <hi>Cain</hi> learn to play the hypocrite, or murther his brother? who was his preſident to imitate? I read not at that time of any vile wretch beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es himſelfe in the whole world, that was guilty of ſuch horrid crimes; ſurely then it muſt be ſomewhat within him, that muſt move him to ſin ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againg the God of heaven and earth, which can be nothing but that <hi>ſeminale principium,</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in lady, that <hi>David</hi> here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes he was conceived and born in: this every man that knows himſelf knows to be true I appeal to the conſcience, eſpecially of a good man, whether he finds not in his nature an inclination to the fouleſt ſin in the world; he that doth not feel this ſuggeſtion of concupiſcence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> dead in diſobedience. Aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y then with this horrid opinion of the Pelagians,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110887:43"/> which is both contrary to the truth of God, and the Saints ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. If Infants were not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then they ſhould need no Saviour, Chriſt dyed in vain for them. But God hath concluded all under ſin, that he might have mercy upon all: nay, how could Infants die if they were not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <hi>death could have no power over them, Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>ult.</hi> which ſin can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not proceed by imitation, then the faculties of Infants ſhould not be corrupted, for they cannot imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate neither good nor evil, yet they have ſin, or they could not die. If it were poſſible to keep any chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from hearing a ly, or ſeeing the practiſe of any filthineſſe or crueltie, yet their very nature up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion offered would carrie them to theſe ſins: ſo that you ſhall find it is not by imitation, but by corruption of nature, that Infants
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110887:43"/> becomes originally ſinful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. This diſcovers the great neceſsity of Infants Baptiſme, which though I do not hold with <hi>Suar.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vt ſi medicus infirmo dixerit, niſi hanc accepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris medicinam non ſanaberis, &amp;c.</note> an intrinſecal neceſſity as he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it by this ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: As if the Phyſician ſhould ſay to his Patient, unleſſe thou take this remedie, thou ſhalt not be healed, implying an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſitie, without which, there can be no ſalvation; yet I hold a neceſſity of the precept and means, it being that Goſpel-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of imitation that doth ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them Diſciples, and doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt their viſibilitie of member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Church of Chriſt: which thing maketh greatly for the confirmation of the ſtrength of their Parents for the preſent,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110887:44"/> and their future comfort after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, that as they are by nature ſo filthy and loathſome in the ſight of God: ſo the Lord hath in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt (whereof the water in Baptiſme is a ſign and ſeal) provided a laver to waſh and clenſe them in, even the laver of regeneration, which, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cals it, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>yea, a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain opened,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1. <hi>for ſin and for unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> ſufficient to clenſe them of all this filthineſſe and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their nature. But here perchance may ſome object.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> If Baptiſme be ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, what ground or precept have you for it out of Gods word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, this will appear unto us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. where Chriſt commands his, Diſciples, and in them all Miniſters ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:110887:44"/> unto the end of the world, to go and diſciple all nations, Baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt; which words of our ſaviour are not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, teach, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, make Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which is by by being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Chriſts School, their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents giving their names to Chriſt both for themſelves and their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies: And in Chriſts precept, teaching doth not go before, but follow baptizing, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>teaching them to obſerve all things, &amp;c.</hi> which is punctually obſerved in the children of the faithfull, who after they are baptized, when they come to years of diſcretion, are taught to obſerve all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Chriſt hath commanded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Though this be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt for the inſtitution
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110887:45"/> of Baptiſme, yet there is not one word of Infants, nor any command giving for baptizing them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, a thing may be ſaid to be commanded in Scripture two waies.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Literally, Syllabically, <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis terminantibus,</hi> in expreſſe termes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Implicitely, by way of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, by good conſequence: though in the former ſenſe Infant-Baptiſme is not commanded, yet in the latter it appears to be, by promiſes, proportions, example, and conſiderations of the like grounds and cauſes, comparing Scripture with Scripture, and look what can be thus proved, is as ſtrong and valid, as though it were commanded in ſo many ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables and letters: What command is there for women to partake of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:110887:45"/> the Lords ſupper? yet the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper with the Paſſeover makes it lawfull: What expreſſe command is there for a Sabbath in the new Teſtament, yet by conſequential grounds it doth appear to be ſo. The leaſt filings of gold, is gold, as well as the whole tag: ſo whatſoever is drawn out of Scripture by juſt conſequence and deduction, is as well the word of God, as that which is an expreſſe commandement or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Scripture,<note place="margin">Tombes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. p. <hi>110. 111.</hi>
               </note> yea a learned Anabaptiſt doth confeſſe, that a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand by way of implication, is equivalent to a command. Now that Infants are thus included, will appear in the word <hi>Nations,</hi> and <hi>Them,</hi> whereof Infants being an eſſential part, without whom, a Nation cannnot ſubſiſt, are inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:110887:46"/> and collectively under the compriſe of Chriſts command: Yea, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2. to the 7th. there you ſhall find a clear place, <hi>à Typo ad veritatem,</hi> from the type to the truth, from the ſignes in the Law, to the thing ſignified in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Aug. in Johan. tract. <hi>26.</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta, illa fuerunt in ſignis diverſa, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quae ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabantur paria.</note> that Infants are to be baptized: For ſaies the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>all our Fathers were under the cloud, and all paſſed through the ſea, and were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized unto</hi> Moſes <hi>in the cloud and in the Sea, &amp;c.</hi> which cloud and ſeawere types of our baptiſm, and did ſhadow it out unto us; and by this <hi>all,</hi> is meant all our Fathers, which ſynechdochically is to be underſtood of all the people of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> both young &amp; old, men, women, and children, they all were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110887:46"/> unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> (1.) under the conduct or guidance of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or into the Doctrine or law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> even the children as well as the parents, as will appear, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.37. for we cannot imagine them ſo unnatural as to leave their children behind them in the wilderneſſe; ſo that it appears plainly, their Baptiſme being the ſame in ſubſtance and ſignification as ours was, that even children by name are within the compaſſe of Chriſts command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> How can ſuch be baptized that are not capable of baptiſm, who have not underſtanding to know any benefit by it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is a two-fold incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, 1. Total,<note place="margin">Capaces ſunt ſpiritus fidei, per quem animos ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiunt eſſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuale ac ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turale, &amp;e.</note> as in ſtocks and ſtones, which have no life
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:110887:47"/> nor reaſonable ſoul for the ſpirit to work upon, as Infants have. 2. Partial, or a proximate incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie which are in Infants, who, though for the preſent are unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of actual faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yet not of the principal and root of both; as they have in them a principal and root of reaſon, though for the preſent they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not act it. Beſides, they are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Baptiſm as well as Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion under the law, ſince they are meerly paſſive in both. For what is circumciſion, but the ſame in ſubſtance with baptiſme, which the Apoſtle calls, <hi>the ſeal of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which is by faith?</hi> Shall then the Goſpel put them in a worſe condition then they were before? this were to abridge the mercie of Chriſt, and draw it into a narrower compaſſe then he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:110887:47"/> who to ſhew his mercy to Infants, did take them into <hi>his armes, and bleſſed them, Mark</hi> 10.14. If then they were capable of bleſſing, when they were not able to go, but muſt be brought to Chriſt, being ſuch as of whom peculiarly the Kingdome of God conſiſts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.6. What then hinders, but that they may be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the early charitie of the Church, in bringing and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to baptiſme (though they doe not underſtand the vow) and receive benefit and advantage by partaking of it: and rather when it is remembered that Chriſt baptized not at all, and ſo thought not to baptize theſe, did yet afford the ceremonie to them, and in the antient Church was prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie and antecedent to baptiſme: <hi>viz.</hi> impoſition of hands, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:110887:48"/> bleſſing them, which they being capable of, ſhews them to be in as great a capacity of baptiſme, it being a paſſive ordinance, when the perſon baptized is a meer pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, as in the caſe of circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>But to admit all further objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the clearing of this truth, it being already manifeſt from the capacity of Infants, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, it is ſufficient to juſtifie the practiſe of Apoſtolicall Miniſters in the advancement of this Ordinance for the good of them. If any deſire to be further ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, hee may confer with the learned worthies of theſe times, as Reverend <hi>Featly,</hi> Reverend <hi>Baxter,</hi> learned <hi>Hamond,</hi> who have ſo clear'd this truth, that he that runs may read a full ſatisfaction in it.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:110887:48"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 3d. Reprove ſuch as think it folly to be troubled with the ſins of litle ones, with their lying and ſwearing, curſing, and the like, not conſidering that the very Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſin of the Infant, the ſin of his nature before it doth thus break forth, makes him odious to God, and deſerveth damnation, much more wil theſe ſame curſed fruits do it? See an example in this, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.23. where thoſe forty that mocked the Prophet were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by Bears: where youth was no excuſe for the hainouſneſſe of their offence, but were ſeverely puniſhed by the hand of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 4. Let this then humble us, in conſidering the ſharp and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere judgments that oft light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on little ones, yea, and take them to heart, and to be much affected with them, as with moſt evident
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:110887:49"/> demonſtrations of Gods wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin, even againſt the ſin of our nature. Our Saviour ſighed, <hi>Mark</hi> 7.34. to behold the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God upon the deaf man, as a ſign of Gods anger upon him for ſin; how much more doth it become us to do ſo in this caſe. The Lord in his judgements upon us, that are of years, may have other ends and reſpects, but in thoſe upon Infants, he can have no other but onely to make known upon them his wrath againſt ſin. Oh that we could ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in this caſe thus expoſtulate with our own ſouls. If God be ſo angry with the ſin of the infant, alas, what meaſure of wrath is due to me, that beſides the ſin of my nature, wherewith I am every whit as much defiled as it can be, have ſo many actuall ſins to anſwer for; and have ſinned in a far more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:110887:49"/> manner then this infant hath done? If this be done to the greene tree (ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.31. <hi>What ſhall be done to the drie;</hi> ſurely this is enough if well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to melt the hardeſt heart into tears throughly to bewaile the Originall corruption eſpecially when they conſider the next point following, namely.</p>
            <p>Doct. 2d. <hi>That the ſin which we are from our very infancie stained withall: is conveyed by our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis Leproſie began in <hi>Adam,</hi> and you ran over all ſucceſſions of mankind. Hence the Prophet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth, <hi>I was conceived in ſin,</hi> not meaning any particular ſin of his Parents, in the act of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, for he was begotten and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110887:50"/> born in lawful marriage: but his hereditary ſin whererof he was guilty in his mothers womb.</p>
            <p>For though many cauſes may be aſſigned of actuall ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by men or women, as either of themſelves, <hi>James</hi> 1.14. the world, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.16. or the devil, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. yet of original ſin that is in Infants, no other cauſe can be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, no root, no fountain, but this, that they received it from their parents. Hence is that of <hi>Aug. per duos homines tranſiſſe pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum.</hi> Both ſaith <hi>Ambroſe, paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ut generis ſic et erroris.</hi> This is agreable to the law of nature, <hi>Partus ſequitur ventrem.</hi> If a free man get a child by a bond-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the child ſhal be bond by the mother, not free by the Father. As ſin entered into Paradiſe, ſo it
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:110887:50"/> entered into the world: for it is the ſame ſin in us that was in them; in them actually, in us originally; and the ſame ſin muſt have the same beginning: but it came into Paradiſe by them both, therefore ſo into the world: And therefore, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.3. it is ſaid, that <hi>Adam</hi> after his fall, <hi>begat a ſon in his likeneſſe, after his image,</hi> ſinful and corrupt as himſelfe was: and the Evangeliſt making an oppoſition between the cauſes from whence corruption and grace cometh, ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 1.13. <hi>The one cometh from bleod, and from the wil of the fleſh, and from the wil of man, but the other commeth from God alone.</hi> Hence there was never any that had parents, (a Father to beget him, and a Mother to conceive him) that was free from this origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſin and corruption of nature:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:110887:51"/> no not ſuch as had the godlieſt Parents that ever lived: as the the children of <hi>Noah, Abraham, Iſaac, David,</hi> did ſtand in need of circumciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.4. which ſignifies the cutting away of the filthy fore-skin of their hearts, this original corruption, as the Prophet expounds it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. wherefore, <hi>Job.</hi> 14.4. when he would give a reaſon why man, every man, young and old, is not only ſubject to ſo many troubles in this life, but alſo ſo filthy and ſinful, alledgeth no more but this, <hi>Man that is born of a woman;</hi> he is born of a woman, and therefore muſt needs be ſo. So again, <hi>Iob</hi> 15.14. and 25.4. and though the Mother only be named by <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> yet is this corruption derived to the child, not from the Mother only, but from the father as much
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110887:51"/> as from the mother. The ſin came by two, and the Apoſtle ſaies it entered by one, for they two made but one, <hi>Two ſhal be one fleſh.</hi> By one it entered, yet both ſinned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> 1. Becauſe all parents have been poyſoned with ſin, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>by their natures being infected, doth convey this poyſon unto their children: As the brood of Vipers, Toads, and Spiders, muſt needs reſemble them, and have poyſon in them. Hence is that of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.18. <hi>a corrupt Tree cannot bring forth good fruit;</hi> for if the tree be not found, the fruit will prove tainted; and therefore ſaith <hi>Iob, Iob</hi> 14.4. <hi>Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?</hi> Not one. This reaſon our Saviour gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth why all that is in man by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is fleſh, that is corrupt and ſinfull, becauſe he that is born of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:110887:52"/> the fleſh, that is, of corrupt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.6. is fleſh, that is, ſinful, which is <hi>Job</hi>'s meaning, when he ſaith, <hi>who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?</hi> that is, no man can beget a child that is clean from ſin, himſelfe being unclean: For ſuch as the fountain is, ſuch is the ſtream, ſuch as the ground is, ſuch is the corn, ſuch as the fuel is, ſuch is the fire, ſuch as the mine is, ſuch is the metal, ſuch as the parents are, ſo are their children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> If the root be holy, the branches are holy; therefore the children of the Saints are holy, and have not this ſin conveyed to them by their parents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Parents beget children as men, not as they are holy men; <hi>Sanctus generat, non regenerat filius carnis:</hi> by generation they derive
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:110887:52"/> unto them their nature, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not derive grace which is above nature; we give them that, which our earthy parents give us, not what our Heavenly Father infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth into us. There is a wide diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt infuſion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation; neither doth holineſſe in this place ſignifie a freedome from ſin, or integritie, or uprightneſſe of nature;<note place="margin">Sanctitas eſt duplex, fidei &amp; faederis, ſancti ſunt non virtute nativitatis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum carnem, ſed virtute Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti gratiae et promiſſionis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i. Bulling.</note> but the prerogative and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſteritie, whereby God covenanting with him, had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed alwaies to convert ſome of his poſteritie, and to give them inward holineſs; ſo that here is meant not any inherent internal qualitative perſonall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, but an external relative fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deral
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:110887:53"/> holineſſe. Hence is that of <hi>Grotius, Non loquitur Apoſtolus de ſanctitate naturali, et naturae libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum inhaerente, ſed de ſanctitate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerente its extrinſice (i. e.) de ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate faederis, credentium liberi faedere gratiae comprehenſi ſunt, et eatenus ſancti adeo cenſentur.</hi> This Text ſhews, that children are ſtil in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with their parents, but proves nothing at all that they are freed from original ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> 2. Becauſe this ſin proceeds cauſally from the fleſh, though ſubjectively and formally it is in the Soul; as ſickneſſe comes of corrupt meats as the cauſe, yet not the meats, but the body is the ſubject of ſickneſſe. They that live in a ſmoakie houſe muſt needs be ſmu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ched, and contract ſome of the blackneſſe: if you put the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt wool into the Die-fat of Oade,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:110887:53"/> it will come out blew: So here a pure ſoul in an impure body cannot but infect it with impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; this then is an hereditary diſeaſe, as a leprous father begets a leprous ſon, the diſeaſe being in the blood, runs through the whole progenie, which verifies that of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 18.2. <hi>The Fathers have eaten ſour grapes, and the childrens teeth are ſet on edge.</hi> And therefore ſaies the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.46. <hi>That was not firſt which was ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, but that which was natural, and afterwards that which was ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. The firſt man was of the earth, earthy,</hi> and ſo begat children like himſelfe, ſinful and corrupt, which was the ground of this ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal contagion, which was ſprung in our parents by their offence; and ſo by the ſame it is conveyed to poſteritie.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:110887:54"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> If ſin be conveyed by the parents to the children, it paſſeth to them either by the body or by the ſoul, but by neither it cannot be in the body till the ſoul come, and in the ſoul it is not, becauſe that is immediately created pure of God. <hi>Ergo,</hi> unleſſe the ſoul be traduced from the parents, where place you original ſin?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The conſequence and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence of the major is to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, becauſe in it there is not a ſufficient numeration of the parts by which original ſin paſſeth: for it paſſeth neither by the body nor by the Soul, but by the offence of our parents; in regard whereof, God, whilſt he createth men ſouls, bereaves it of originall righteouſneſſe, which he gave on that condition to our firſt parents, that they ſhould continue or loſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:110887:54"/> them to poſteritie, according as themſelves either kept or loſt them; which privation of righteouſneſſe, in reſpect of God, for mans of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, is not a ſin, but a juſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, though in reſpect of the parents which draw it unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their poſteritie, it be a ſin; which through the conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of both, is conveyed from the parents unto their children; ſo neither the body alone, nor the ſoul is to be reſpected, but as they joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make one man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. This may meet with the proud hearts of men, who are ready to advance themſelves in reſpect of their birth and paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, which if they did truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, this Doctrine would rather humble them, ſeeing nothing is derived from them but baſeneſſe and corruption, their natures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:110887:55"/> vile, contaminats their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and inſtead of making them honourable, doth make them odious in the pure eyes of God, yea, and moſt miſerable for ever, if they be not born again, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.3. if we got not a better birth then that which we had from our parents, it may be ſaid of us, as it was ſaid of <hi>Iudas, it had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for us that we had never been born, Mat.</hi> 26.24. It is reported of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> that he told <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, that he could know no difference betwixt the bones of King <hi>Philip</hi> and other men: what he ſpake of dead men lying in the ground, holds true of all men living, ſo long as they lie in the grave of ſin, there is no difference betwixt the greateſt and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, for all are by nature ſinful, and this ſin of our nature is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:110887:55"/> from the fathers to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; ſo that here is no cauſe of boaſting, but rather matter of abaſement, whereby the beſt may be humbled upon the ſenſe of this their condition. The greatneſſe of birth through thy corruption makes thee more uncapable of grace, then thoſe of meaner degree. <hi>You ſee your calling brethren</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. and ſurely ſo may we now) <hi>how that not many great men, not many noble are called:</hi> Even greatneſſe of birth &amp; nobility is a bar oftentimes to keep men from ſalvation, and life eternal; though, bleſſed be God, ſome great men are called, yet there are but few, <hi>not many,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle. O what madneſſe then is it to reſt and glory in our birth, in that we were born of ſuch parents, and never ſeek to be born of God.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:110887:56"/> This is that which makes men truly honorable, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come truly gratious. Hence 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. <hi>They that honor God, them will God honor.</hi> As they of <hi>Berea, Acts</hi> 17.11. <hi>were more noble then they of Theſſalonica, ſhewing the fruits of grace, in receiving the word with all readineſſe of mind.</hi> And thus if our nobilitie appears, we may take comfort in our eſtate, otherwiſe we may be abaſed for the ſadneſſe of our condition. Be not then like the bigger the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; hills the higher the barrener; but like unto a Diamond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. This may ſerve to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all parents in the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe ſins that break forth in their childrens lives, their pride and ſtubbornneſſe, their averſeneſſe from God and prophanneſſe, all which is by them the cauſe of great
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:110887:56"/> ſorrow and humiliation. Hence is that of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 10.1. <hi>A fooliſh Son is the heavineſſe of his mother.</hi> And 17.25. <hi>A fooliſh Son is a grief to his father, and bitterneſſe to her heart that bare him.</hi> For the root, from whence all this evill ſpringeth, they had from their Parents: the plague-ſore of ſin was conveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, and this they were infected with from their very birth. In the time of the plague, we count it a great affliction to bring the infection into our houſes, and ſet it upon our children; and yet we have all done worſe to our children then this, we have ſet upon them a farre more dangerous and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſeaſe, which doth not only ſlay the body, but overthrow the Soul, and that everlaſtingly,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:110887:57"/> if God look not in mercy upon them. 1 If the Lord was angry with the Serpent, and had laid a curſe upon it, becauſe it was but an inſtrument uſed by the Devil, for the corrupting of our firſt parents, though it were no cauſe of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.14. how much more reaſon hath he to be angry with us, that have not only been inſtruments to convey this curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed contagion of nature into our children, but the principall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents and cauſes of it. Oh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider then this, you that forget God, that have no care in the education and bringing up of your children in the knowledge of the waies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, ye have much to anſwer for at the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal ſeat of Chriſt, that having conveyed poyſon into your children at their birth, you ſeek
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:110887:57"/> not after the antidote to prevent their eternal ruine: wil you be inſtruments to wound their ſouls, and never ſeek after a Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon to heal them? ſhall you be the cauſe of giving a deadly potion that will work their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, and never have recourſe to the Phyſician in their behalfe to cure them? Oh, here's a curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neglect! Be abaſhed therefore in the thoughts of this, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not your ſoules be ſo ſecure, as to endanger your own eternal welfare by neglecting the dutie in preventing your childrens woe; but be humbled for them your ſelves, being the cauſe of their inbred maladie, which by you were conveyed unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 3d. Exhort to ſtir up pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to do their utmoſt to work grace in their children, and ſo
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:110887:58"/> to cure that deadly poyſon and infection that they have convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into them. Now for the better enforcing ſo neceſſary a dutie, I will ſet down</p>
            <p n="1">1. Certain motives that may provoke them to this care.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Diſcover the means that they muſt uſe to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mot.</hi> 1. Becauſe of that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral affection that we bear to our children, whereby we are moved to love them, hence bowels of pitty and compaſſion appears towards them, when we ſee them in any miſerie. And therefore the Lord hath been pleaſed to ſet forth his mercy and compaſſion towards his children, by the compaſſion of a Mother. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Can a Mother forget her ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing child, that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the ſon of her womb?</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:110887:58"/> And by the compaſſion of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 103.13. <hi>Like as a Father pittieth his children, ſo the Lord pittieth them that fear him.</hi> He is worſe then a beaſt that pittieth not his children, and grieves not to ſee them in miſerie <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Even the Sea-monſters draw out the breaſt, they give ſuck to their young ones.</hi> Yea, where there is not natural affection, there the very light of nature is extinguiſhed, and ſuch in the juſt judgment of God, are given up unto a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate mind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.31. Now what love can we bear to our children, if we have no care of their ſouls; the nature of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is to ſeek the good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their ſouls whom we love: as <hi>Abraham</hi> expreſſed his love to <hi>Iſhmael, Gen.</hi> 17.18. <hi>O that Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:110887:59"/> might live in thy ſight,</hi> which ſhould be the deſire of all godly parents, Oh that my children might live in thy ſight! that they might fear thee, and know thee, and learn truly to ſerve thee: this is the greateſt portion that can be given them, the largeſt poſſeſſions we can deſire to leave them, as that they may live in the ſight of God: <hi>For god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is the greateſt gain, and hath the promiſes of this life, and of a better,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. Strive then to make your children god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and let the bent of your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections towards them lie that way, and if they become once ſincerely to love God, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve you ſhewed natural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the higheſt degree towards them, which at the laſt will bring not only grace
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:110887:59"/> to them, but glory for ever to your ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. <hi>Mot.</hi> Becauſe the rule of juſtice requires that we ſhould make them amends for the wrong we have done them; if we injure any man in body, goods, or good name, we are bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to make him ſatisfaction: See the equitie of Gods Law in this point, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.19. <hi>He that ſmote him ſhal pay for the loſs of his time, and ſhal cauſe him to be thoroughly healed;</hi> how much more are we to be careful to cure the inbred maladie of our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to heal that filthy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, which from our ſelves have been conveighed unto them? Shal we be the cauſes of their miſerie, and not uſe our beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to cure them? It is
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:110887:60"/> through us that they become odious aſſoon as they are born in the ſight of God, and ſhal not we ſeek to make them amiable and lovely in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? ſhall we be the progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of their evil, and not the promoters of their good? Oh far be it from us to be ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful of our own dutie, and ſo neglectful in not uſing all means for their good. This was that which good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> meant in his prayer, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.18, 19. <hi>The grave cannot praiſe thee, death cannot celebrate thee, the living ſhal praiſe thee</hi> (and who among the living?) <hi>the Father to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhal make known thy truth.</hi> Hence is that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Epb.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Ye fathers bring up your children in the nurture and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the Lord.</hi> And ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:110887:60"/> 78.5. <hi>He eſtabliſhed a Teſtimony in</hi> Jacob, <hi>and appointed a Law in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which he commanded our Fathers that they ſhould make them known unto their Children.</hi> Let all parents therefore, think of this ſeriouſly, and conſider, that it will be a moſt heavy rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning one day they muſt give for the neglect of their childrens ſouls; thoſe eſpecially, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of reforming them, do to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate them in moſt ſinful courſes, as in lying, ſwearing, Sabbath-breaking, and the like; theſe are far from <hi>Abraham's</hi> practiſe <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. and <hi>Joſuah's</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 24.15. that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed their families, and brought their children to fear the Lord. Conſider then this motive, you that deſire to ſerve the Lord; remember it is but
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:110887:61"/> juſtice to ſeek after all means to doe your children good; you have wrong'd them greatly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow recompence that wrong you have done them by ſeaſoning their tender years with the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3d. Becauſe the propagation of Religion dependeth princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally in the education of our children. To this purpoſe you have a notable example of this care in the two Tribes and the half, that had their poſſeſſions given them beyond <hi>Jordan Ioſuah.</hi> 2.24, 25. we have done it (ſet up this Altar) for fear of this thing, ſaying, <hi>In time to come your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren might ſpeak to our Children:</hi> ſaying, <hi>what have you to do with the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael? ſo ſhall your Children make our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ceaſe from fearing the Lord.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:110887:61"/> Concerning which you muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that there is no man doth ſo much deſire to have a poſterity, and to provide for poſterity as the Lord doth. And ſurely the meanes whereby the Lord may have a poſterity rayſed and preſerved is, to derive Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion unto them, when Parents are not onely Religious them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but be careful to provide that their Children may be ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. This is that Seminary of Gods Church. Here was the cauſe of that Commandment. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Take heed to thy ſelf, and keep thy ſoul diligently, leſt thou forget the things which thine eyes have ſeen, and leſt they depart from thy heart all the daies of thy life; but teach them thy ſon, and thy ſons ſons.</hi> This is made by the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> 2.15. to have been the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:110887:62"/> cauſe why the Lord at the firſt inſtitution of marriage, appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but one woman for one man, and did ſo reſtrain promiſcuous luſt, that he might ſeek a ſeed of God; that is, that he might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the continuance of his Church. And that is one princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall end. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.29, 30. in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of us Gentiles unto the Goſpell, and men of all ſorts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, poor and rich, that our ſeed might ſerve him, and might be accounted unto the Lord for a generation: that God might have a poſterity and a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſerve him when wee are gone. How ſhould then this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us in the education of our children, ſeeing the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Religion doth thus greatly depend upon it. How ſhould wee ſeek to train them up
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:110887:62"/> in the fear of God, and ſo ſeaſon their tender years with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, that they may be inſtruments to glorifie the God of their Fathers, and to continue faithfull in their ſervice to him all the daies of their life. If Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were but carefull in this, then ſhould they find that of the wiſe man to prove true, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.6. <hi>That their Childrens Children would be a crown of old age,</hi> and be an enlargement of the greateſt comforts unto their ſouls; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as on the contrary, if Parents be neglective in this, it will adde to the ſtore of their confuſion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe of that heavie charge God hath given Parents concerning their children. For this they muſt know, that their children are not their own but the Lords. Hence <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:110887:63"/> The Lord ſaies, <hi>thy ſons and thy daughters whom thou haſt born un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, thou haſt taken and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed.</hi> And as we have begotten and born them for him, ſo hath he charged us to educate and bring them up for him. And that with ſuch a charge as the Prophet telleth <hi>Ahab</hi> in a parable, that he had received for the keeping of a man committed to his truſt in the battell 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.39. <hi>If by any means he be miſſing, thy life ſhall be for his life.</hi> If the childs ſoul periſh) through the Parents default, whom God put in truſt to keep and look to it) the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſoul muſt die for it. For this is the righteous ſentence of God againſt them, whom he hath char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the ſoules of others. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.18. <hi>He ſhall die in his iniquity, but his blood will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:110887:63"/> at thy hand:</hi> but ſome will here ſay, this charge concernes the Miniſters not the Parents; I anſwer, that every Parent is as deeply charged by God with the ſouls of his children, as any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor with the ſoules of his flock, and more deeply too. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſhew thy ſon the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the end, and uſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the paſſover,</hi> and <hi>Deut.</hi> 6 6, 7. <hi>Theſe words which I command thee this day, thou ſhalt teach them diligently to thy children;</hi> which place diſcovers expreſly the care that Parents ſhould have towards their childrens ſoules; that they might not be careleſſe in their duty, in their behalf to inſtruct and teach their children according to the command of God. Oh the ſhamefull neglect that Parents herein are guilty of?
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:110887:64"/> how do they ſuffer their children to run into all manner of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, and never ſeek to reſtrain or reform them in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Surely the doom will lie heavie one day on their ſoules for this horrible neglect of their duty in failing to inſtruct their Children. Oh conſider this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times all you that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the bleſſings of Children un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; remember that thoſe ſweet babes are but lent to you from God, that you might bring them up in his fear, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come babes of grace: and let it be your endeavours ſo to inſtruct them, as that God may have the glory, and your ſouls reap the comfort in thus diſcharging your duty.</p>
            <p>And for further direction, let us be carefull to uſe theſe means
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:110887:64"/> which will further us in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of our duty, towards cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that inbred maladie, which is conveyed from our ſelves to our children.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us ſeek to inſtruct them in the fear of God: this God hath appointed to prepare their hearts, and make them more capable of Grace. Hence <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.3, 4. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith <hi>when he was young and tender his Father taught him:</hi> yea and his Mother too. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.1. yea, hee oft putteth Gods people in mind, not onely of the inſtruction and charge they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from their Fathers; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Law and Doctrine of their Mothers. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.6.26. which ſheweth plainly it was the practiſe of the Church of God then; that even Mothers were teachers of their Children. Hence
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:110887:65"/> that direction comes ſeaſonable to Parents. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22 6. <hi>Train up a child in his way,</hi> ſaies Solomon, that is, that way that is fit for him according to his capacity, as hee is able to receive it by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle at once, as pouring out liquor into narrow mouth'd bottles: to move beyond the ſphere of their activity is to prejudice their capacity; and therefore we muſt be tender of their condition, leſt we hinder their reception of inſtruction. Young children are like the twiggs of trees, which being young wil bend to our minds, but if much bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will break in pieeces. So if we do not much oppreſſe the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of children, they will bee ready to receive the inſtructions we give them, but if herein wee burden them, they will grow
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:110887:65"/> dul and weary in wel doing, we muſt then be careful of the meaſure of inſtruction, that ſo giving them according to their capacity, they may receive comfort and benefit by it: To this end we muſt acquaint them with the practiſe of religion, as reading the Word and Prayer, giving of thanks at their meat, and ſinging of Pſalmes. We ſhall find, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.15. That the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children had learned of their parents to ſing Hoſanna, part of the hundred and eighteen Pſalm, to the praiſe of Chriſt, yea more then this, parents ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to reſtrain their children from evil, and to breed in them a conſcience of ſin, even while they are young, to bring them to the publick worſhip of God, and to examine them how they
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:110887:66"/> profit under the means of grace; to wit, how they underſtand plain what they hear, and to make it to them; and in thus doing, they wil learn in time to know the wil of God, and in knowing of it, to come to the practiſe of the ſame, to the glory of God, and their own eternal comfort.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Acquaint them betimes with the knowledge of Gods word; for this is life eternal, to know Chriſt as he is revealed in his word. It is a true ſaying, (which though the expreſſion be homely) we have our children as we breed them; if we ſuffer them to lye, ſwear, and diſhonour God in their Infancy, we ſhal ſee the fruits of it in riper years; but if we ſeaſon their tender years with the knowledge of God in his word, we ſhal ſee
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:110887:66"/> the comfortable fruits of this in our lives, the tender plants are pliable to bend,<note place="margin">Quo ſemel eſt imbutea recens ſervabit odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem teſtadiu: Habitus diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culter mobiles.</note> which once grown trees, become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexible. An habit in ſin is hard to be removed, which by timely prevention of frequent acts in the practiſe of holineſſe may be hindred: It is therefore a ſeaſonable advice given by <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Remember thy creator in the daies of thy youth:</hi> Youth being that ſpring time, wherein ſhould appear the hopeful bloſſomes of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if not blaſted through the parents neglect, for want of timely inſtruction. It's a rare character which God gives of <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18.19. and takes notice of him on this ſcore, in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:110887:67"/> that he knew he would inſtruct his children in the fear of his name: Happy then are thoſe parents that herein imitate faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Abraham,</hi> timely to acquaint their children with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God: God will own ſuch as he did <hi>Abraham,</hi> and give them the bleſſings of his right hand, with the greateſt joy and comfort. Hence we may ſay with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 127.3. <hi>Lo chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are an heritage of the Lord.</hi> And verſe 5. <hi>Happy is the man that hath his quiver ful of them; they ſhal not be aſhamed, but they shal ſpeak with their enemies in the gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Cauſe them to frequent the publick worſhip of God, when you have the ſpouts of grace powring forth incomparable ſweetneſſe and comfort, on the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:110887:67"/> ſoules of all ſuch as ſhall attend and wait upon it. We find, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.9. that <hi>Moſes</hi> told <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that they muſt have the little ones with them to ſolemnize the worſhip they were to perform to God in the wilderneſſe. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but add much joy to the parents to hear their children ſing the ſong of Sion, before they have known the ditties of ſin, and to ſpeak plainly the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> before they have been corrupted with the expreſſions of <hi>Aſhdod:</hi> Cauſe them therefore to frequent the publick worſhip, where the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt doth moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly appear, not only in the tender of his grace and mercy for our childrens good, but in the choice embracings of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ligious endeavours, who have
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:110887:68"/> been educated in the fear of his holy name. It is a practiſe much to be condemned in many pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, in that they are careleſſe of their childrens good, in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to frequent the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip of God; they doe rather tolerate them to ſtay at home, to be nurſed in prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ignorance, then to cauſe them to frequent the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip of God, where they may be directed to walk in the comfortable paths of grace and holineſſe; it is to be feared that ſuch children one day will have cauſe to curſe their parents in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgency; yea, their very parents, for this neglect may expect, that thoſe darlings of theirs, when they ſhould become their greateſt comforts, to prove the greateſt croſſes and grief of heart unto
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:110887:68"/> them. Be adviſed then you pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents that are herein guilty, remember the doctrine you have read, that you conveigh nothing but corruption to your children; and will you add fuell to the fire, be guilty of more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury in keeping your children from the publick worſhip of God? let this be far from you ſo to doe, but rather endeavour as to acquaint them betimes with the knowledge of God, ſo to cauſe them to frequent his publick worſhip, where they ſhal find great comfort and ſweetneſſe adminiſtred unto their ſouls.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Give good ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to them, that by your light they may ſhine in a continued light of holineſſe and pietie. This made <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 101.2. <hi>reſolve to walk in his houſe with
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:110887:69"/> a perfect heart.</hi> And <hi>Job Job,</hi> 11.14. to ſay, <hi>let not wickedneſſe dwel in thy Tabernacles.</hi> The looſe lives of parents, do too often prove much injurious to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens ſouls; ſo that we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in the childrens practice, the fathers guilt of their impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Hence you have it in the proverb, that when the child ſwears, the Chicken crows but as it hears the old Cock; and if the father reprove, the child is ready to ſay, <hi>Medice cura teip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum:</hi> Father, reform thy ſelfe, if thou hadſt brought me up better, I had learned to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: this is the fruits of a bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, which parents muſt learn to avoid, if they deſire, either to diſcharge their own dutie, or to ſave their poor childrens ſouls. Learn then, Oh parents,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:110887:69"/> to cull out the beſt examples for your children, be ye followers of Chriſt, that they may follow you in the waies of Chriſt; let your light ſo ſhine in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God before them, that they may ſee your good works, to glorifie their father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Do not with <hi>Samſon</hi> pull down thoſe pillars of goodneſſe by your ſins, that ſhall not only quaſh your ſelfe, but be the ruine of your children; your facts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come examples, thoſe examples laws; and it is natural for your children to follow the law of fact, before the law of faith, a viſible pattern, rather then a meer audible Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Examine your children how they profit by the means of grace; this is the means to ſharpen, and whet them on
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:110887:70"/> your children; uſe in this caſe makes perfect, and the more fit for the practiſe of holineſſe: A pious education is a great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of thoſe groſs evils which their natures are prone to commit. Examination is the tryal which by grown experience encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges their practiſe in old age; hence are they ready to praiſe God for the care and zeal their parents had in their education: and conſidering the progreſſe they have made in the waies of Chriſt under God; they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to acknowledge it from their Parents care, which muſt needs cauſe great comfort to them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, be earneſt to God by prayer for them. <hi>Solomons</hi> Mother <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.2. calleth him the Son of her youth. She was wont to pray much for him: what great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:110887:70"/> comfort can ariſe to the child when grown in years, then to conſider he was the Son of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents prayers: they begg'd him of God, and God gave a returne to their prayers in giving grace unto him. There are too many herein faulty in the neglect of their duty, both for themſelves and their children: yea, they are ſo farre from praying for them, as that they are too ready upon the leaſt occaſion to curſe them bitterly: What comfort can theſe expect from the hands of God, either for themſelves or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? but that the Lord might juſtly plague them in their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring in ſuffering their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to prove the greateſt croſſes; whom otherwiſe had yielded the greateſt comforts? Let us then with <hi>Hannah</hi> pray for our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:110887:71"/> and with <hi>Monica</hi> pray for the ſalvation of them, prayer is requiſite, that we may be new born in grace, and that being ſo born, wee may grow in grace. Prayer it is the Key to open the gates of Heaven and let grace out; and prayer is a lock to faſten our hearts, and keep grace in. Let all Parents therefore be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to bee earneſt to God by prayer for their children; So ſhall they waſh away thoſe ſtains wherewith they have polluted their childrens ſouls, and take away that guilt they have brought upon them by conveying their corruption unto them. That whereas by nature they are the children of wrath and heirs of Hell, God hearing their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in their childrens behalf, will make his promiſe not onely to be
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:110887:71"/> their God, but the God of their ſeed in making them the ſons of God, and children of light to ſhine as ſtarres in the firmament of glory. To which he bring both us and our children for his ſake who hath ſo dearly bought us, even Jeſus Chriſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. <hi>To whom with the Father and bleſſed ſpirit, three perſons but one God be aſcribed all glory and honor now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edm. Calamy.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110887:72"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
